{"tossups": [{"question": "This man forced the Armistice of Mudanya upon his enemies, triggering the downfall of David Lloyd George\u2019s government. This man\u2019s opposition to the Treaty of Sevres allowed him to win a more favorable territorial settlement in the Treaty of Lausanne. After consolidating power, this man\u2019s \u201cSix Arrows\u201dideology promoted a new Latin alphabet for the country and banned the fez. For ten points, name this man who established a new capital at Ankara after founding modern-day Turkey", "answer": "Mustafa<b> Kemal</b> (accept<b> Ataturk</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A position outside this city was fortified by Rufus Putnam during one event whose end is celebrated as Evacuation Day. During one battle, Henry Knox reinforced this city\u2019s Dorchester Heights with cannons from Fort Ticonderoga. This city was besieged by American forces following the battles of Lexington and Concord. The Battle of Bunker Hill was fought outside of, for ten points, what Massachusetts city where British troops had earlier committed a namesake massacre?", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man arrested William Burroughs after he opposed this man\u2019s plans to sail to the Isle of Terceira. This man destroyed at least 27 Spanish ships at the Bay of C\u00b4adiz in the Singeing of the King of Spain\u2019s Beard. This man sacked Santo Domingo and captured Cartagena de Indias in 1586 before fortuitously rescuing Walter Raleigh\u2019s Roanoke Colony. For ten points, name this Elizabethan captain of the<em> Golden</em> <em>Hind</em> who circumnavigated the world from 1577 to 1580.", "answer": "Sir Francis<b> Drake</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s government planned but failed to attack a western neighbor in Project National Glory. Peace Memorial Day commemorates a massacre by this man\u2019s regime known as the 228 Incident. This Commandant of the Whampoa Academy was kidnapped by Zhang Xueliang during the Xi\u2019an Incident, forcing him to collaborate with a group that would later force this husband of Soong Mei-Ling to flee to Taiwan. For ten points, name this leader of the Kuomintang who lost the Chinese Civil War to Mao Zedong.", "answer": "<b> Chiang</b> Kai-Shek (accept<b> Jiang</b> Jieshi, accept<b> Chiang</b> Chongchen)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One book written in this language argued that God did not choose to create the universe, but that his divine nature caused the universe to be. Another book in this language argued that memory is the result of continued abstraction or spiritualization. Another work in this language was criticized by Aquinas for its introduction of the \u201cunity of the intellect.\u201d For 10 points, name this language used by al-Farabi, Averroes, and other Islamic commentators on Aristotle.", "answer": "<b> Arabic</b> or<b> al-Arabiyyah</b> or<b> Arabi</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In this city, Ambassador Graham Martin was picked up by \u201cLady Ace 09\u201d whose crew had orders to arrest him if he attempted to stay. The USS<em> Blue Ridge</em> was so overloaded by one event in this city that its crew began throwing vehicle s into the sea. Irving Berlin\u2019s \u201cWhite Christmas\u201d was used to begin a series of evacuations in this city that began after the shelling of Tan Son Nhat airport. Operation Frequent Wind was a series of helicopter evacuations of, for ten points, what capital of South Vietnam that was renamed after its fall in 1975?", "answer": "<b> Saigon</b> (accept<b> Ho Chi Minh City</b> before it is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This site included the Mach\u2019ay Cave, where young boys had their ears pierced as a rite of passage. At this site, the Watana Stone was arranged to point at the sun during winter solstices. This site\u2019s other religious buildings included the Room of the Three Windows and the Torreon. Located above the Sacred Valley, this site was discovered when the Urubamba River was traversed by Hiram Bingham\u2019s party. For ten points, identify this \u201cLost City\u201d of the Incas.", "answer": "<b> Macchu Picchu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Vala attempted to flee this battle during fighting at Kalkriese hill. A campaign waged in vengeance for this battle culminated in the Battle of Idistaviso, which was won by Germanicus. This battle\u2019s winning commander led an alliance of tribes including the Cherusci. This battle\u2019s result caused Augustus to rage,\u201cQuintilius Varus, give me back my legions!\u201d Arminius and his German allies inflicted, for ten points, what decisive 9 AD Roman defeat in a namesake forest?", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Teutoburg Forest</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In a work by this author, a man becomes obsessed with and then terrified by an infinitely long book. When reflecting on a conflict, this author called a war in his country \u201ctwo bald men fighting over a comb.\u201dThis author described a point in space that contains all other points in one work, and described a system of infinite hexagonal rooms in his \u201cLibrary of Babel.\u201d For ten points, name this author of \u201cThe Zahir,\u201d\u201cEl Aleph,\u201d and \u201cThe Garden of Forking Paths.\u201d", "answer": "Jorge Luis<b> Borges</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "A picture taken in this location shows Kerry and Caroline Kennedy peeking out of an open door. An item in this location was built from timbers salvaged from a British ship that was abandoned in the Arctic; that piece of furniture was re-installed in this location in 1977, although the C&O Desk was preferred by George H.W. Bush. The Blue Room\u2019s distinctive bowed walls inspired the design of, for ten points, what room in the West Wing of the White House, the primary office space for the President?", "answer": "<b> Oval Office</b> (prompt on descriptive partial answers, like \u201cthe President\u2019s office\u201d; prompt on West Wing and/or White House before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In one work of this type, which ends with the words \u201chorror, horror, horror,\u201d the narrator meets her fianc\u00b4e Jean Moraweicki and volunteers at the Union G\u00b4en\u00b4erale des Isra\u00b4elites en France. Another one of these works ends with the lines \u201cthe Savichevs are dead. Everyone is dead. Only Tanya is left.\u201d That work was presented at the Nuremburg Trials alongside another work of this type, which was addressed \u201cDear Kitty\u201d and was written while in hiding in Amsterdam. For ten points, name this type of personal work kept by H\u00b4el\u00b4ene Berr and Anne Frank.", "answer": "World War II<b> diary</b> (or<b> journal</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Paul Weber taught many artists from this movement, which was influenced by the D\u00a8usseldorf School. William Sidney Mount promoted this school as part of the Young America Movement. A poet and a painter stand on a rock and look out at the Catskills in a painting from this movement,<em> Kindred Spirits</em>. For ten points, name this American art movement whose members included Frederic Edwin Church, Asher Durand, and Thomas Cole, named for a New York waterway.", "answer": "<b> Hudson River</b> School", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man founded the New York Manumission Society and had earlier drafted a state law to abolish slavery. This man served as the U.S. chief negotiator at the Treaty of Paris. In<em> West v. Barnes</em>, this man refused to establish judicial review. The 11th amendment overturned a decision made by this man\u2019s court in<em> Chisholm v. Georgia</em>. This man signed a namesake 1795 treaty with Great Britain. For ten points, name this Founding Father and first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.", "answer": "John<b> Jay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Angelo Massarelli compiled six unpublished volumes of records from this event. In response to Diogo de Andrada\u2019s criticism of his works, Martin Chemnitz wrote a four-volume examination of this event. Charles Borromeo led the final session of this council, during which the index of forbidden books was published. The spread of Protestantism prompted Pope Paul III to convene, for ten points, what Catholic council that outlined the tenets of the Counter-Reformation?", "answer": "Council of<b> Trent</b> (or<em><b> Concilium Tridentinum</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This technology company, which launched an \u201cEats\u201d food delivery platform in 2014, controversially operated during a New York City taxi strike. For ten points, name this rideshare company that competes with Lyft.", "answer": "<b> Uber</b> Technologies, Inc.", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This process will allow anyone to purchase stock in the company and allow founders and early employees to cash out their stock.", "answer": "<b> I</b>nitial<b> P</b>ublic<b> O</b>ffering (accept going<b> public</b>, accept becoming a<b> public</b>ly-traded company, accept anything about being listed on a stock exchange) <b></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>A 2015 study on DNA from this bacteria preserved in human teeth claimed that this bacteria emerged 5,000 years ago and caused pandemics in the Bronze Age. DNA from this bacteria from skeletons in Aschheim Cemetery, Bavaria proved that this bacteria caused a</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>6th century pandemic. A 2018 model of this bacteria\u2019s transmission argues that fleas</b> <b>and ticks, instead of (*)</b> rats, were most likely responsible for spreading this bacteria during its most famous pandemic. For ten points, name this bacteria which caused pandemics during Justinian\u2019s reign and the Black Death.", "answer": "<em><b> Y</b>ersinia<b> pestis</b></em> (accept<b> plague</b>, accept<b> bubonic plague</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this ethnic group, members of which were the plantiffs in the<em> Hirabayshi</em> and<em> Korematsu</em> cases.", "answer": "<b> Japanese</b>-Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Berestov Mount in this city was given to the Monastery of the Caves by Iziaslav Yaroslavich, who faced a 1068 revolt after this city was defeated by the Cumans at the (+) Alta River. Boleslaw the Great led an expedition to this city during a succession crisis detailed by Nestor in his (*)</b><em> Primary Chronicle</em>, a history of a state centered in this city that included that struggle between Sviatopolk and Yaroslav the Wise as well as Grand Prince Vladimir\u2019s conversion to Christianity. For ten points, what capital city of a Rus federation is the modern-day capital of Ukraine?", "answer": "<b> Kiev</b> (accept<b> Kiev</b>an Rus\u2019 or Principality of<b> Kiev</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The director of this film began a tradition by staying away from the set for the shooting of its last scene; he was afraid of his crew after filming took 100 more days than expected. Robert Shaw plays the obsessed Quint in this film, which held the record for highest box</b> <b>office gross from (+)</b> <b>1976 until the release of</b><em><b> Star Wars</b></em><b> and revolutionized the idea of</b> <b>1976 until the release of</b><em><b> Star Wars</b></em><b> and revolutionized the idea of</b> <b>the summer blockbuster. Martin Brody quips \u201cYou\u2019re (*)</b> <b>the summer blockbuster. Martin Brody quips \u201cYou\u2019re (*)</b> gonna need a bigger boat\u201d in, for ten points, what classic thriller with a John Williams score, a Steven Spielberg film about a resort town terrorized by a killer shark?", "answer": "<b> Jaws</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This composer wrote a mass named for the wife of Francis II, Maria Theresa of Naples and Sicily. A melody by this composer was used for the hymn \u201cGod Save Emperor Francis.\u201d</b> <b>This composer\u2019s (+)</b> <b>\u201cTrauer\u201d symphony is typical of his Sturm und Drang phase. After</b> <b>the Battle of the Nile, this composer\u2019s</b><em><b> Mass for Troubled Times</b></em><b> was nicknamed for Lord Nelson. A melody from this composer\u2019s (*)</b><em> Emperor</em> string quartet is used as the German national anthem. For ten points, name this composer of just over a hundred symphonies with nicknames such as\u201cFarewell\u201d and \u201cSurprise.\u201d", "answer": "Franz Joseph<b> Haydn</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man led a colonial force that fought alongside Mingo soldiers led by Tanacharison, who supposedly washed his hands in the brains of an opposing leader. This man remarked</b> <b>that \u201cI (+)</b> <b>heard the bullets whistle and, believe me, there is something charming in the</b> <b>sound\u201d in a letter to his brother John in May 1754 after a battle in which (*)</b> Joseph Coulon de Villiers died. Roughly a month after the Battle of Jumonville Glen, this Lieutenant Colonel surrendered at Fort Necessity. For ten points, name this American colonial leader who, years later, decidedly did not surrender as Commander-in-Chief of the Continental Army.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One member of the all-female Cumann na mBan [man] that participated in this event,</b> <b>Elizabeth O\u2019Farrell, negotiated the end of this event. A ship disguised as the (+)</b> <b>SS Aud</b> <b>failed to deliver weapons to this event. Michael Mallin led forces on Saint Stephen\u2019s Green during this event, after which one side\u2019s leaders were executed at (*)</b> Killingham Gaol. Those leaders included Joseph Plunkett and Patrick Pearse, who led the Volunteers during this event. The General Post Office was occupied in, for ten points, what 1916 insurrection that tried to establish an independent Ireland?", "answer": "<b> Easter</b> Rising or Rebellion", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}